# Lucas de Oliveira Gelape

Political scientist and data analyst. I have experience with computational social sciences, especially in political, socioeconomic and social media data analyses. I have also graduated in Law and was a full-time graduate student for four years.

#### **Education**

## University of São Paulo

OPhD in Political Science 2017–2021

## **Harvard University**

Visiting Fellow 09/2019–02/2020

#### Federal University of Minas Gerais

MA in Political Science 2015–2017

# Federal University of Minas Gerais

Bachelor in Laws 2010–2014

# **Professional Experience**

#### Center for Politics and Economics of the Public Sector, FGV-SP

Post-Doctorate Researcher

May 2023-Currently

Post-Doctorate Researcher. Project: "The spatial voting patterns of local elections and their related variables", associated with the project "Electoral strategies and public policies: what is the importance of municipalities?", supervised by prof. George Avelino.

#### Fundação SEADE - São Paulo State Statistical Bureau

Technical Adviser

Jan. 2022-Mar. 2023

Technical Adviser at the Data Production Analysis Division. The tasks focused on managing and executing activities using new technologies to produce official statistics: text-as-data machine learning models; development and maintenance of ETL processes; web scraping; creation of indicators; opening and standardizing public data.

#### Volt Data Lab

Data Analyst

Feb. 2019-Aug. 2019; Jun. 2020-Jan. 2022

Activities of data collection, analyses, and visualization in several projects of the agency. Among them, the development of social listening platforms, data analyses for several stories on *Núcleo Jornalismo* and other projects in the agency, and software development (R packages) to extract API data.

## G1 (Rede Globo)

Data Scientist Jul. 2018–Nov. 2018

Data collection, data analysis, and wrote news stories about the Brazilian general elections.

## Instructor on programming and quantitative methods' courses

Teaching experience 2017–2023

Taught the following short courses: *Introduction to Statistics (using R)* (Modus-UFMG, 2019 e 2021), *Spatial Data Analysis* (IESP-UERJ's Winter School, 2023), *The use of maps in Political Science* (workshop at the VIII Seminar of Political Science and International Relations, UFPE, 2019), *Introduction to Spatial Data Analysis* (Meios-UFMG, 2017), and *Introduction to R* (UFMG Law School, 2017, and a workshop at Coda.BR, 2022).

# Languages

English: Proficient.Italian: Advanced.Spanish: Intermediate.

# **Technical Skills**

## Programming Languages:

R: Advanced.SQL: Beginner.TeX: Beginner.Stata: Beginner.

## Softwares:

QGis: Intermediate. ArcGis: Beginner.

# **Courses and Training**

#### Methodology:

- Summer Institute in Computational Social Science (FGV-DAPP, 2022)
- Introduction to Machine Learning (Curso-R, 2021)
- Dashboards with R (Curso-R, 2020)
- Survey Research Design (IPSA-USP, 2019)
- Survey Research Analysis (IPSA-USP, 2019)
- Introduction to Survey Experiments (IPSA-USP, 2019)
- Field Research: Interviewing and Mixed Methods (IPSA-USP, 2018)
- Basics of Spatial Interdepence in Theory and Practice (IPSA-USP, 2018)
- Aggregate Data Analysis (MQ-UFMG, 2016)
- Spatial Data Analysis and Visualization (MQ-UFMG, 2016)
- Linear Regression (MQ-UFMG, 2015)